Min Si

 $\label{eq:minsii.github.io} \begin{array}{l} \texttt{minsii.github.io} \mid \texttt{minsi.atwork@gmail.com} \mid (\texttt{Mobile}) + 1 \ 630\text{-}880\text{-}4388 \\ \texttt{linkedin.com/in/minsi-atwork} \mid \texttt{github.com/minsii} \mid \texttt{Naperville}, \ \texttt{IL} \ 60540 \\ \texttt{Research Scientist}, \ \texttt{Facebook} \end{array}$

Highlights: Research interests include parallel programming models and HPC runtime systems. Lead research and development of one-sided communication models including MPI RMA and OpenSHMEM for HPC systems. Experienced in project management and staff supervision.

Education

Education	
Ph.D. in Computer Science Department of Computer Science Graduate School of Information Science and Technology The University of Tokyo	2012/10 – 2016/03 Tokyo, Japan
Master of Science Department of Computer Science Graduate School of Information Science and Technology The University of Tokyo	2010/10 – 2012/09 Tokyo, Japan
Bachelor of Arts Department of Japanese Language and Culture College of Oriental Languages Sichuan International Studies University	2003/09 - 2007/07 Chongqing, China
Professional Experience	
Research Scientist Facebook, CA, USA • HPC hardware/software co-design for AI.	2021/06 - Current
Assistant Computer Scientist Argonne National Laboratory, IL, USA • OpenSHMEM implementation over MPI (PI). • High performance MPI implementation (Co-PI). • Data management and runtime optimizations for AI workflow (Senior Personnel). • Supporting infrastructure for surrogate benchmarks on HPC systems (Senior Personnel).	2018/05 - 2021/06
Enrico Fermi Postdoctoral Scholar Argonne National Laboratory, IL, USA • Dynamic execution runtime (PI). • High performance MPI implementation (Co-PI).	2016/10 - 2018/04
Postdoctoral Appointee Argonne National Laboratory, IL, USA • High performance MPI implementation.	2016/05 - 2016/09
Guest Graduate Student Argonne National Laboratory, IL, USA • MPI optimization on massively parallel multi-/many-core architectures.	2014/05 - 2016/03
Research Aide Argonne National Laboratory, IL, USA • Multithreaded MPI for many-core environments.	2013/05 - 2013/09
Summer Internship NEC Corp, Tokyo, Japan • InfiniBand driver modification for direct data transfer from/to FPGA board.	2011/08 - 2011/11
Part-time Programmer Secioss Corp, Tokyo, Japan • E-commerce web system development using PHP.	2010/12 - 2011/12
Full-time Engineer Kinotrope Inc, Tokyo, Japan Web system (CMS E commerce Auto test) development using PHP	2008/07 - 2010/09

• Web system (CMS, E-commerce, Auto-test) development using PHP.

Curriculum Vitae of Min Si Page 2

Full-time Engineer

• Credit card member management system development using Java.

2007/07 - 2008/04DGT Information Systems Ltd, Shanghai, China

Project Leadership

OpenSHMEM over MPI: Analyzing and Improving the Suitability of MPI as an OpenSHMEM Runtime.

- PI. Period: 01/2021 present. Technical Lead and Core Developer. Period: 08/2018 to 12/2020.
- Leading research and development of OpenSHMEM over MPI implementation. Managing project milestones and reporting to DOD program managers. Participating at OpenSHMEM specification committee and contributing to specification revisions. Serving as the committee RMA working group chair since 2020/11.
- Websites: http://www.mcs.anl.gov/project/oshmpi, https://github.com/pmodels/oshmpi
- Supervision (1 Postdoc):

Huansong Fu: Postdoctoral Research Associate, period: 03/2019 to 08/2019. Predoctoral Research Associate, period: 08/2018 to 12/2018. Ph.D. student, Florida State University, USA, period: 05/2018 to 08/2018.

MPICH: A high-performance, portable implementation of the Message Passing Interface (MPI).

- Co-PI and Core Developer. Period: 10/2016 to present.
- Leading research and development of MPI RMA model and shared memory based communication. Driving new research directions such as optimizing runtime system for AI on HPC and using AI in communication system. Contributing to MPI RMA specification revision.
- Websites: http://www.mpich.org, https://github.com/pmodels/mpich
- Supervision (4 Graduate students):

Michael Wilkins: Ph.D. student, Northwestern University, USA. Period: 08/2020 to 11/2020.

Li Cao: Master student, University of Chicago, USA. Period: 08/2020 to 12/2020.

Subhadeep Bhattacharya: Ph.D. student, Florida State University, USA. Period: 05/2019 to 08/2019.

Sarunya Pumma: Ph.D. student, Virginia Tech, USA. Period: 08/2016 to 01/2017.

Braid: Data Flow Automation for Scalable and FAIR Science.

- Senior Personnel. Period: 10/2020 to present.
- Leading research and development of AI/DL data management and optimization on HPC systems. Co-working with Dr. Bogdan Nicolae.
- Supervision (1 Graduate student):

Jie Liu: Ph.D. student, University of California, Merced, USA. Period: 01/2021 to present.

Beehive: A Dynamic Execution Environment for Performance, Power, and Resilience on Extreme-Scale Computing Systems.

- PI and Core Developer. Period: 10/2016 to 03/2020.
- Leading research and development of the Beehive eco-system. Managing project milestones and reporting to Argonne LDRD program office. Collaborating research with Intel, RIKEN Japan, and BSC Spain.
- Website: http://www.mcs.anl.gov/project/casper, https://github.com/pmodels/casper
- Supervision (2 Graduate students):

Kaiming Ouyang (joint project with MPICH): Ph.D. student, University of California, Riverside, USA. On PhD committee. Period: 10/2018 to present.

Yanhao Chen: Ph.D. student, Rutgers University, USA. Period: 05/2018 to 08/2018.

Honors and Awards

The University of Tokyo, Japan

Hollors and Awards	
Impact Argonne Award for Extraordinary Effort Argonne National Laboratory, USA	2020/08
IEEE-CS Technical Consortium on High Performance Computing (TCHPC) Early Career Researchers Award for Excellence in High Performance Computing. SC 2018, USA	2018/11
Best Paper Award at the 27th ACM International Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (Top 1/112). HPDC 2018, USA	2018/06
Enrico Fermi Fellowship for Postdoctoral Scientists Argonne National Laboratory, USA	2016 - 2018
Dean's Award for Outstanding Achievement Doctoral Course The University of Tokyo, Japan	2016/03
Fellowship Special Scholarship Program for International Students	2012 - 2015

Curriculum Vitae of Min Si Page 3

Computer Science Research Award for Young Scientists Information Processing Society of Japan (IPSJ), Japan 2012

Selected Publications and Presentations

Refereed Journal Articles

- 1. S. Pumma, M. Si, W. Feng, and P. Balaji. Scalable Deep Learning via I/O Analysis and Optimization. In *ACM Transactions on Parallel Computing (TOPC)*, vol. 6, no. 2, pp. 1–34. June, 2019.
- 2. M. Si, A. J. Peña, J. Hammond, P. Balaji, M. Takagi, and Y. Ishikawa. Dynamic Adaptable Asynchronous Progress Model for MPI RMA Multiphase Applications. In *IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems (TPDS)*, vol. 29, no. 9, pp. 1975–1989. September, 2018.

Research Papers in Refereed Conferences (peer-reviewed)

- 1. K. Ouyang, M. Si, A. Hori, Z. Chen, and P. Balaji. CAB-MPI: Exploring Interprocess Work-Stealing toward Balanced MPI Communication. In *Proceedings of the International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage and Analysis (SC 2020)*. IEEE Press, Article 36, 1–15. (Acceptance Rate: 25.4%)
- 2. A. Amer, C. Archer, [et al, including **M. Si**]. Software Combining to Mitigate Multithreaded MPI Contention. In *Proceedings of the 33rd ACM International Conference on Supercomputing (ICS 2019)*, pages 367–379. June 2019. (Acceptance Rate: 23%)
- 3. A. Hori, M. Si (Joint First Co-Author), B. Gerofi, M. Takagi, J. Dayal, P. Balaji, and Y. Ishikawa. Process-in-Process: Techniques for Practical Address-Space Sharing. In *Proceedings of the 27th International Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC 2018)*, pages 131–143. June 2018. Best Paper Award. (Acceptance Rate: 19.6%)
- 4. Sarunya Pumma, M. Si, Wu-Chun Feng, and P. Balaji. Parallel I/O Optimizations for Scalable Deep Learning. In *Proceedings of 2017 IEEE 23rd International Conference on Parallel and Distributed Systems (ICPADS 2017)*, pages 720–729. December 2017.
- 5. M. Si and P. Balaji. Process-based Asynchronous Progress Model for MPI Point-To-Point Communication. In Proceedings of 2017 IEEE 19th International Conference on High Performance Computing and Communications (HPCC 2017), pages 206–214. December 2017. (Acceptance Rate: 38%)
- 6. Sarunya Pumma, **M. Si**, Wu-Chun Feng, and P. Balaji. Towards Scalable Deep Learning via I/O Analysis and Optimization. In *Proceedings of 2017 IEEE 19th International Conference on High Performance Computing and Communications (HPCC 2017)*, pages 223–230. December 2017. (Acceptance Rate: 38%)
- 7. K. Raffenetti, A. Amer, [et al, including M. Si]. Why is MPI so Slow? Analyzing the Fundamental Limits in Implementing MPI-3.1. In *Proceedings of the International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage and Analysis (SC 2017)*, pages 62:1–62:12. November 2017. (Acceptance Rate: 18%)
- 8. M. Si, A. J Peña, J. Hammond, P. Balaji, M. Takagi, and Y. Ishikawa. Casper: An Asynchronous Progress Model for MPI RMA on Many-Core Architectures. In *Proceedings of the IEEE/ACM International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS 2015)*, pages 665–676, May 2015. (Acceptance Rate: 21.8%)
- 9. M. Si, A. J Peña, J. Hammond, P. Balaji, and Y. Ishikawa. Scaling NWChem with Efficient and Portable Asynchronous Communication in MPI RMA. In *Proceedings of 8th IEEE International Scalable Computing Challenge Colocated with IEEE/ACM CCGrid 2015*, pages 811–816, May 2015. (Acceptance Rate: 33%)
- 10. **M. Si**, A. J. Peña, P. Balaji, M. Takagi, and Y. Ishikawa. MT-MPI: Multithreaded MPI for Many-core Environments. In *Proceedings of the 28th ACM International Conference on Supercomputing (ICS 2014)*, pages 125–134. May 2014. (*Acceptance Rate: 21%*)

Research Papers in Refereed Workshops (peer-reviewed)

- 1. M. Si, Y. Ishikawa, and M. Tatagi. Direct MPI Library for Intel Xeon Phi Co-Processors. In *Proceedings of the 2013 IEEE 27th International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium Workshops PhD Forum (IPDPSW)*, pages 816–824, May 2013.
- 2. M. Si and Y. Ishikawa. Design of Direct Communication Facility for Many-Core Based Accelerators. In Proceedings of the 2012 IEEE 26th International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium Workshops PhD Forum (IPDPSW), pages 924-929, May 2012.

Thesis

1. **Min Si**. Techniques For Enabling Highly Efficient Message Passing on Many-Core Architectures. Dissertation. Department of Computer Science, Graduate School of Information Science and Technology, The University of Tokyo, Japan. March 2016.

Curriculum Vitae of Min Si Page 4

2. Min Si. Communication Facility in Manycore-based Cluster System. Master Thesis. Department of Computer Science, Graduate School of Information Science and Technology, The University of Tokyo, Japan. September 2012.

Invited Talks

General HPC Runtime Systems.

- Challenges and Opportunities in Co-Design for High-Performance Computing Software Systems Invited talk at UMN Cloud Data Center and Edge (CDCE) workshop, 2021/02
- Co-Design for High-Performance Computing Software Systems. REBASE talk at ACM SIGPLAN conference on Systems, Programming, Languages, and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH 2020).
- AI@Edge: Software System Implications. *Microelectronics Workshop at Argonne National Laboratory*, October 2019.

OpenSHMEM.

- OpenSHMEM over MPI: A Performance Contender. OpenSHMEM Birds of a Feather (unofficial) at SC20.
- OpenSHMEM over MPI: Capabilities and Challenges. OpenSHMEM Birds of a Feather at SC19.
- Performance Analysis of MPI RMA in Supporting OpenSHMEM Runtime. OpenSHMEM Birds of a Feather at SC18.
- OpenSHMEM over Portable MPI RMA with Asynchronous Progress Support. OpenSHMEM Birds of a Feather at SC17.

Beehive and MPI.

- Towards Dynamic Communication Runtime for Scalable Irregular Parallel Computing. Florida State University, December 2018.
- Towards Portable and Adaptable Asynchronous Communication for One-Sided Applications. Tenth International Workshop on Parallel Programming Models and Systems Software for High-End Computing (P2S2 2017).
- Data Locality Challenges in Irregular Applications for Exascale Programing. Fourth Workshop on Programming Abstractions for Data Locality (PADAL 2017).

Professional Services and Activities

Editorial Affiliations

- IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems (IEEE TPDS). Co-Editor of Special Section on Parallel and Distributed Computing Techniques for AI, ML and DL in 2021, 2020.
- Software: Practice and Experience (SPE). *Co-Editor* of Special Issue on: New Trends in High Performance Computing: Software Systems and Applications in 2021.
- International Journal of Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience (CCPE). Guest Co-Editor of the Special Issue on Programming Models and Applications for Multicores and Manycores (PMAM) in 2021, 2020, 2019. Guest Co-Editor of the Special Issue on Parallel Programming Models and Systems Software (P2S2) in 2021-2020.
- Elsevier International Journal of Parallel Computing (PARCO). Guest Co-Editor of the Special Issue on Applications and System Software for Hybrid Exascale Systems (AsHES) in 2019, 2018. Guest Co-Editor of the Special Issue on Parallel Programming Models and Systems Software (P2S2) in 2019, 2018. Guest Co-Editor of the Special Issue on Programming Models and Applications for Multicores and Manycores (PMAM) in 2018.

Chair and Co-Chair - Conferences / Workshops

- IEEE International Conference on High Performance Computing, Data, and Analytics (HiPC). *Program Track Vice-chair* of 2021.
- IEEE Symposium on High Performance Interconnects (HOTI). Program Co-Chair of 2021.
- International Workshop on Accelerators and Hybrid Emerging Systems (AsHES), held in conjunction with IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS). *General Chair* of 2021, 2020. *Program Co-Chair* of 2019, 2018.
- International Workshop on Parallel Programming Models and Systems Software for High-End Computing (P2S2), held in conjunction with International Conference on Parallel Processing (ICPP). *Program Co-Chair* of 2021, 2020, 2019, 2018. *Publicity Chair* of 2016.
- International Workshop on Programming Models and Applications for Multicores and Manycores (PMAM), held in conjunction with Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming (PPoPP). *Program Co-Chair* of 2021, 2020, 2019.
- International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC). *Panels Vice-Chair* of 2019.

Curriculum Vitae of Min Si Page 5

• IEEE International Conference on Cluster Computing (Cluster). Financial Chair of 2022. Virtual Arrangements Co-Chair of 2021.

- European MPI Users Group Meeting (EuroMPI). Financial Chair of 2020. Financial Co-Chair of 2017. Web Co-Chair of 2018.
- International Conference on High Performance Computing in Asia-Pacific Region (HPC Asia). *Program Track Co-Chair* of 2021.

Committee Member - Conferences / Workshops

- International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage and Analysis (SC). TPC Member of 2021, 2020. Panels PC Member of 2021.
- IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS). TPC Member of 2021. Workshops Committee Member of 2020, 2019, 2018, 2017.
- ACM International Conference on Supercomputing (ICS). TPC Member of 2021, 2020, 2018. External Review Committee Member of 2019.
- ACM SIGPLAN/SIGBED International Conference on Languages, Compilers, and Tools for Embedded Systems (LCTES). TPC Member of 2021.
- ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming (PPoPP). TPC Member of 2018. External Review Committee Member of 2021, 2020.
- IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Cluster, Cloud and Grid Computing (CCGrid). TPC Member of 2019, 2018, 2017.
- IEEE International Conference on Cluster Computing (Cluster). TPC Member of 2021, 2018, 2017.
- International Conference on Parallel Processing (ICPP). TPC Member of 2021, 2019.
- European MPI Users Group Meeting (EuroMPI). TPC Member of 2019, 2018, 2017.
- Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies (OpenSHMEM). TPC Member of 2018, 2017.
- Supercomputing Asia conference (SCA). TPC Member of 2019, 2018.
- International Symposium on High Performance Interconnects (HOTI). TPC Member of 2017.
- IEEE International Conference on High Performance Computing and Communications (HPCC). TPC Member of 2017.

Journal Referee

- IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems (TPDS). 2020, 2019, 2018, 2017, 2014.
- IEEE Transactions on Computers (TC). 2020, 2019.
- IEEE Transactions on Cloud Computing (TCC). 2017.
- IEEE Transactions on Multi-Scale Computing Systems (TMSCS). 2018, 2017.
- Journal of Parallel and Distributed Computing (JPDC). 2020, 2019, 2018, 2017, 2016, 2015.
- Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience (CPE). 2017, 2016
- Elsevier International Journal of Parallel Computing (PARCO). 2020, 2018, 2017, 2016.
- International Journal of Parallel Programming (IJPP). 2018, 2016.